Funding for this program is provided by
Additional funding provided by
When we ended last time, we were
discussing Locke's idea of government by consent.
And the question arose, what are the limits on
government that even the agreement of the majority can't override?
That was the question we ended with.
We saw in the case of property rights,
that on Locke's view,
a democratically elected government has
the right to tax people.
It has to be taxation with consent, because it does
involve the taking of people's property for the common good.
But it doesn't require the consent of each individual
at the time the tax is enacted or collected.
So, we're going to look at the tax.
What it does require
is a prior act of consent to join the society,
to take on the political obligation.
But once you take on that obligation,
you agree to be bound by the majority.
So much for taxation.
But what you may ask about the right to life,
can the government conscript people
and send them into battle?
What about the idea that we own ourselves?
Isn't the idea of self-possession violated?
If the government can, through
coercive legislation and enforcement powers,
say, you must go risk
your life to fight in Iraq,
what would Locke say? Does the
government have the right to do that?
Yes.
In fact, he says in 139,
he says,
what matters is that the political authority,
or the military authority,
not be arbitrary. That's what matters.
And he gives a wonderful example. He says,
a sergeant, even a sergeant,
let alone a general, a sergeant can command a soldier
to go right up to the face of the cannon,
where he is almost sure to die.
That the sergeant can do.
The general can condemn the soldier
to death for deserting his post,
or for not obeying even a desperate order.
But with all their power over life and death,
what these officers can't do
is take a penny of that soldier's money.
Because that has nothing to do with the rightful authority.
That would be arbitrary.
And it would be corrupt.
So, consent winds up being very powerful in Locke.
Not consent of the individual to
the particular tax or military order,
but consent to join the government
and to be bound by
the majority in the first place.
That's the consent that matters.
And it matters so powerfully
that even the limited government created
by the fact that we have
an unalienable right to life, liberty, and property,
even that limited government is only limited in the sense
that it has to govern by generally applicable laws,
the rule of law, it can't be arbitrary.
That's Locke.
Well, this raises a question about consent.
Why is consent such a powerful moral instrument
in creating political authority and the obligation to obey?
Today we begin to investigate the question of consent
by looking at a concrete case,
the case of military conscription.
Now, some people say,
if we have a fundamental right
that arises from the idea that we own ourselves,
it's a violation of that right
for government to conscript citizens to go fight in wars.
Others disagree.
Others say that's a legitimate power of government,
of democratically elected governments.
But that's not the case, anyhow,
and that we have an obligation to obey.
Let's take the case of the
United States fighting a war in Iraq.
News accounts tell us that the military
is having great difficulty meeting its recruitment targets.
Consider three policies that the U.S. government,
U.S. government might undertake
to deal with the fact that
it's not achieving its recruiting targets.
Solution number one,
increase the pay and benefits
to attract a sufficient number of soldiers.
Option number two,
shift to a system of military conscription.
Have a lottery,
and whosoever numbers are drawn,
go to fight in Iraq.
System number three,
outsource.
Hire what traditionally have been called mercenaries,
people around the world who are qualified,
able to do the work,
able to fight well,
and who are willing to do it
for the existing wage.
So let's take a quick poll here.
How many favor increasing the pay?
Huge majority.
How many favor going to conscription?
One, two.
All right, maybe a dozen people in the room
favor conscription.
What about the outsourcing solution?
Okay, so there may be,
what, two, three dozen.
During the Civil War,
the Union used a combination
of conscription and the market system
to fill the ranks of the military
to fight in the Civil War.
It was a system that began with conscription,
but if you were drafted
and didn't want to serve,
you could hire a substitute to take your place.
And many people did.
You could pay whatever the market required
in order to find a substitute.
People ran ads in newspapers.
In the classified ads.
Offering $500,
sometimes $1,000,
for a substitute who would go fight the Civil War
in their place.
In fact, it's reported that Andrew Carnegie
was drafted
and hired a substitute to take his place
for an amount
that was a little less
than the amount he spent in a year
on fancy cigars.
Now, I want to get your views
about the Civil War system.
Call it the hybrid system.
Conscription, but with a buyout provision.
How many think it was a just system?
How many would defend the Civil War system?
Anybody?
One? Anybody else?
Two? Three?
Four? Five?
How many think it was unjust?
Most of you don't like the Civil War system.
You think it's unjust.
Let's hear an objection.
Why don't you like it?
What's wrong with it?
Yes?
Well, by paying $300 for,
to be exempt one time around,
you're really putting a price on the,
on valuing human life.
And we established earlier
that's really hard to do.
So, they're trying to accomplish something
that really isn't feasible.
Good.
So, paying someone $300 or $500 or $1,000.
You're basically saying
that's what their life is worth to you.
That's what their life is worth.
It's putting a dollar value on life.
That's good.
And what's your name?
Liz.
Well, who has an answer for Liz?
You defended the Civil War system.
What do you say?
If you don't like the price,
then you have the freedom
to not be sold or hire.
So, it's completely up to you.
And I don't think it's necessarily putting
a specific price on you.
And if it's done by himself,
I don't think there's anything necessarily
morally wrong with that.
So, the person who takes the $500, let's say,
he's putting
his own price on his life
or on the risk of his life.
And he should have the freedom
to choose to do that.
Exactly.
What's your name?
Jason.
Jason. Thank you.
Now, we need to hear from another critic
of the Civil War system.
Yes.
It's a kind of coercion almost
to people who have lower incomes.
For Carnegie, he can totally ignore the draft.
$300 is irrelevant in terms of the cost.
It's not something that's
in the hands of his income.
For someone of a lower income,
they're essentially being coerced to draft,
to be drafted.
Or, I mean, it's probably they're not able
to find a replacement.
Tell me your name.
Sam.
All right.
So, you say, Sam,
that when a poor laborer buys his,
accepts $300 to fight in the Civil War,
he is in effect being coerced by that money,
his economic circumstances.
Whereas Carnegie can go off,
pay the money,
and not serve.
All right.
I want to hear if someone has a reply
to Sam's argument
that what looks like a free exchange
is actually coercive.
Who has an answer to Sam?
Go ahead.
I'd actually agree with him in saying that.
You agree with Sam?
I agree with him in saying that it is coercion
in the sense that it robs the individual
of his ability to reason.
Okay.
And what's your name?
Raul.
All right.
So, Raul and Sam agree
that what looks like a free exchange,
free choice, voluntary act,
is actually, it involves coercion.
It's profound coercion of the worst kind
because it falls so disproportionately
upon one segment of the society.
Good.
So, Raul and Sam have made a powerful point.
Who would like to reply?
Who has an answer for Sam and Raul?
Go ahead.
I just, I don't think that these drafting systems
are really terribly different from,
you know, all volunteer army sort of recruiting strategies.
The whole idea of, you know, having benefits
and pay for joining the army is, you know,
sort of a coercive strategy to get people to join.
It is true that, you know,
it is true that
military volunteers come from disproportionately,
you know, lower economic status and also, you know,
from certain regions of the country where you can use,
like, the patriotism to try and coerce people
to feel like it's the right thing to do,
to volunteer and go over to Iraq.
And tell me your name.
Emily.
All right.
Emily says, and Raul,
you're going to have to
reply to this, so get ready.
Emily says, fair enough.
There is a coercive element to the Civil War system
when the laborer takes the
place of Andrew Carnegie for $500.
Emily concedes that.
But she says, if that troubles
you about the Civil War system,
shouldn't that also trouble you
about the volunteer army today?
And let me, and before you answer,
how did you vote on the first poll?
Did you defend the volunteer army?
I didn't vote.
You didn't vote.
No.
By the way, you didn't vote.
Did you sell your vote to
the person sitting next to you?
No.
All right.
So what would you say to that argument?
I think that the circumstances are different
in that there was conscription in the Civil War.
There is no draft today.
And I think that the volunteers,
and I think that the volunteers for the army today
have a more profound sense of patriotism
that is of an individual choice
than those who were forced into
the military in the Civil War.
Somehow less coerced.
Less coerced.
Even though there is still inequality in American society.
Even though, as Emily points out,
the makeup of the American military is
not reflective of the population as a whole.
Let's just do an experiment here.
How many here have either served in the military
or have a family member
who has served in the military?
In this generation, not parents.
Family members.
In this generation.
And how many have neither served
nor have any brothers or sisters who have served?
Does that bear out your point, Emily?
Yes.
All right.
Now we need to hear from...
Most of you defended the idea of the all-volunteer military.
Overwhelmingly.
And yet, overwhelmingly, people considered
the Civil War system unjust.
Sam and Raoul articulated reasons for
objecting to the Civil War system.
It took place against a background of inequality,
and therefore the choices people made
to buy their way into military service
were not truly free, but at least partly coerced.
Then, Emily extends that argument
in the form of a challenge.
All right.
Everyone here who voted in favor of the all-volunteer army
should be able...
should have to explain, well,
what's the difference in principle?
Doesn't the all-volunteer army
simply universalize the feature
that almost everyone found objectionable
in the Civil War buyout provision?
Did I state the challenge fairly, Emily?
Yes.
Okay.
So we need to hear from
a defender of the all-volunteer military
who can address Emily's challenge.
Who can do that?
Go ahead.
The difference between the Civil War system
and the all-volunteer army system
is that in the Civil War,
you're being hired not by
the government but by an individual.
And as a result, different people
who get hired by different individuals
get paid different amounts.
In the case of the all-volunteer army,
everyone who gets hired is hired by the government
and gets paid the same amount.
It's precisely the universalization
of essentially paying your service,
of paying your way into the
army that makes the all-volunteer army just...
Emily?
I guess I'd frame
the principle difference slightly differently.
On the all-volunteer army, it's possible
for somebody to just step aside
and not really think about the war at all.
It's possible to say, well, I don't need the money.
I don't need to have an opinion about this.
I don't need to feel obligated to
take my part and defend my country.
With an explicit draft, then there's the threat at least
that every individual will have
to make some sort of decision
regarding military conscription.
And perhaps in that way, it's more equitable.
It's true that Andrew Carnegie
might not serve in any case,
but in one, he can completely step aside from it.
In the other, there's some level of responsibility.
While you're there, Emily, so what system do you favor?
Conscription?
I would be hard-pressed to say, but I think so,
because it makes the whole
country feel a sense of responsibility
for the conflict instead of having
a war that's maybe ideologically supported
by a few, but only if there's no real responsibility.
Good. Who wants to reply? Go ahead.
So I was going to say that the fundamental difference
between the all-volunteer army and then
the army in the Civil War
is that in the all-volunteer
army, if you want to volunteer,
that comes first, and then the pay comes after,
whereas in the Civil War system,
it's the same.
The people who are accepting
the pay aren't necessarily doing it
because they want to.
They're just doing it for the money first.
What motivation beyond the pay do you think is operating
in the case of the all-volunteer army?
Like patriotism for the country?
Patriotism. Well, what about...
And a desire to defend the country.
I mean, there is some motivation in pay,
but the fact that it's first and foremost
an all-volunteer army will
motivate them, I think, personally.
Do you think it's better... And tell me your name.
Jackie.
Jackie, do you think it's better
if people serve in the military
out of a sense of
patriotism than just for the money?
Yes, definitely, because the people who...
That was one of the main
problems in the Civil War army
is that the people that
you're getting to go in it,
or to go to war, aren't
necessarily people who want to fight,
and so they won't be as
good soldiers as they will be
had they been there because they wanted to be.
All right, what about Jackie's...
Having raised the question of patriotism,
that patriotism is a better
or a higher motivation than money
for military service.
Who would like to address that question?
Go ahead.
Patriotism absolutely is not necessary
in order to be a good soldier,
because mercenaries can do just as good of a job
of the job as anyone
who waves the American flag around
and wants to defend what the
government believes that we should do.
Did you favor the outsourcing solution?
Yes, sir.
And, all right, so let Jackie respond.
What's your name?
Philip.
What about that, Jackie?
So much for patriotism.
If you've got someone whose heart
is in it more than another person's,
they're going to do a better job.
When it comes down to the wire and there's, like,
a situation in which someone has
to put their life on the line,
someone who's doing it because they love this country
will be more willing to go into danger
than someone who's just getting paid.
They don't care.
They've got the technical skills,
but they don't care what happens
because they really have...
They have nothing, like, nothing invested in this country.
There's another aspect, though.
Once we get onto the issue of patriotism,
if you believe patriotism, as Jackie does,
should be the foremost consideration and not money,
does that argue for or against
the paid army we have now?
We call it the volunteer army,
though if you think about
it, that's a kind of misnomer.
A volunteer army, as we use
the term, is a paid army.
So what about the suggestion that patriotism
should be the primary motivation for military service,
not money?
Does that argue in favor of
the paid military that we have,
or does it argue for conscription?
And just to sharpen that point,
building on Phil's case for outsourcing,
if you think that the all-volunteer army,
the paid army, is best
because it lets the market allocate positions
according to people's needs,
people's preferences and willingness to serve
for a certain wage,
doesn't the logic that takes you
from a system of conscription
to the hybrid civil war system,
to the all-volunteer army,
doesn't the idea of expanding freedom of choice
in the market,
doesn't that lead you all the way,
if you follow that principle consistently,
to a more personalized army?
And then if you say no,
Jackie says no,
patriotism should count for something,
doesn't that argue for going back to conscription?
If by patriotism you mean a sense of civic obligation.
Let's see if we can step back
from the discussion that we've had
and see what we've learned
about consent
as it applies to market exchange.
We've really heard two arguments,
two arguments against
the use of markets and exchange
in the allocation of military service.
One was the argument raised
by Sam and Raul,
the argument about coercion.
The objection that
letting the market allocate military service
may be unfair
and may not even be free
if there's severe inequality in the society,
so that people who buy their way into military service
are doing so not because they really want to,
but because they have so few economic opportunities
that that's their best choice.
And Sam and Raul say there's
an element of coercion in that.
That's one argument.
Then there is a second objection
to using the market to allocate military service.
That's the idea
that military service shouldn't be treated
as just another job for pay
because it's bound up with patriotism
and civic obligation.
This is a different argument
from the argument about unfairness
and inequality and coercion.
It's an argument that suggests
that maybe where civic obligations are concerned,
we shouldn't allocate duties and rights
by the market.
Now, we've identified two broad objections.
What do we need to know to assess those objections?
To assess the first, the argument
from coercion, inequality,
and unfairness, Sam.
We need to ask,
what inequalities in the background conditions of society
undermine the freedom of choices people make
to buy and sell their labor?
Question number one.
Question number two,
to assess the civic obligation patriotism argument,
we have to ask,
what are the obligations of citizenship?
Is military service one of them or not?
What obligates us as citizens?
What is the source of political obligation?
Is it consent?
Or are there some civic obligations we have,
even without consent,
for living and sharing in a certain kind of society?
We haven't answered either of those questions,
but our debate today about the Civil War system
and the all-volunteer army has at least raised them,
and those are questions we're going to return to
in the coming weeks.
Do you think you should be
able to bid for a baby
that's up for adoption?
That's Andrew's challenge.
Do I think I should be
able to bid for a baby?
I'm not sure.
It's a market.
I mean, I...
Today I'd like to turn our attention
and get your views
about
an argument over the role of markets
in the realm of human reproduction and procreation.
Now, with infertility clinics,
people advertise for egg donors.
And from time to time in the Harvard Crimson,
ads appear for egg donors.
Have you seen them?
There was one that ran a few years ago
that wasn't looking for just any egg donor.
It was an ad that offered a large financial incentive
for an egg donor from a woman
who was intelligent, athletic,
at least 5'10",
and with at least 1,400 or above on her SATs.
How much do you think
the person looking for this egg donor
was willing to pay?
What would you guess?
I'll show you the ad.
$50,000 for an egg.
But only $100,000.
That's a lot of money.
But only a premium egg.
What do you think about that?
Well, there are also sometimes ads
in the Harvard Crimson and other college newspapers
for sperm donors.
So the market in reproductive capacities
is an equal opportunity market.
Well, not exactly equal opportunity.
They're not offering $50,000 for sperm.
But there is a company,
a large commercial sperm bank,
that markets sperm.
It's called California Cryobank.
It's a for-profit company.
It imposes exacting standards
on the sperm it recruits.
And it has offices
in Cambridge between Harvard and MIT
and in Palo Alto near Stanford.
Cryobank's marketing materials
play up the prestigious source of its sperm.
Here is from the website of Cryobank
the information.
Here they talk about the compensation.
Although compensation should not be
the only reason for becoming a sperm donor,
we are aware of the considerable time
and expense involved in being a donor.
So, do you know what they offer?
Donors will be reimbursed $75 per specimen,
up to $900 a month
if you donate three times a week.
And then they add,
we periodically offer incentives such as...
Oh.
Such as movie tickets.
Or gift certificates for the extra time and effort
expended by participating donors.
It's not easy to be a sperm donor.
They accept fewer than 5% of the donors who apply.
Their admission criteria are more demanding than Harvard's.
The head of the sperm bank said
the ideal sperm donor is six feet tall,
with a college degree, brown eyes,
blonde hair, and dimples.
For the simple reason that these are the traits
that the market has shown the customers want.
Quote, quoting the head of the sperm bank,
if our customers wanted high school dropouts,
we would give them high school dropouts.
So, here are two instances,
the market in eggs for donation
and the market in sperm,
that raise a question.
A question about whether eggs and sperm
should or should not be bought and sold for money.
As you progress,
as you ponder that,
I want you to consider another case
involving a market
and in fact a contract
in human reproductive,
in the human reproductive capacity.
And this is the case
of commercial surrogate motherhood.
And it's a case that wound up in court.
Some years ago.
It's the story of Baby M.
It began with William and Elizabeth Stern,
a professional couple wanting a baby,
but they couldn't have one on their own,
at least not without medical risk to Mrs. Stern.
They went to an infertility clinic
where they met Mary Beth Whitehead,
a 29-year-old mother of two,
the wife of a sanitation worker.
She had replied to an ad
that the center had placed,
seeking the service of a surrogate mother.
They made a deal.
They signed a contract
in which William Stern agreed
to pay Mary Beth Whitehead
a $10,000 fee
plus all expenses
in exchange for which
Mary Beth Whitehead agreed
to be artificially inseminated
with William Stern's sperm
to bear the child
and then to give the baby
to the Sterns.
Well, you probably know
how the story unfolded.
Mary Beth gave birth
and changed her mind.
She decided she wanted to keep the baby.
The case wound up in court
in New Jersey.
So let's take,
put aside any legal questions
and focus on this issue
as a moral question.
How many believe
that the right thing to do
in the Baby M case
would have been to uphold
the contract,
to enforce the contract?
And how many think
the right thing to do
would have been
not to enforce that contract?
So it's about,
the majority say enforce.
So let's now hear the reasons
that people had
either for enforcing
or refusing to enforce this contract.
First from those,
I want to hear from someone
in the majority.
Why do you uphold the contract?
Why do you enforce it?
Who can offer a reason?
Yes.
Stand up.
It's a binding contract.
All the parties involved
knew the terms of the contract
before any action was taken.
It's a voluntary agreement.
The mother knew what she was getting into.
The, all four,
intelligent adults,
regardless of formal education,
whatever.
So it makes sense
that if you know what you're getting into beforehand
and you make a promise,
you should uphold that promise in the end.
Okay.
A deal is a deal in other words.
Exactly.
And what's your name?
Patrick.
Is Patrick's reason
the reason that most of you
in the majority
favored upholding the contract?
Yes?
All right.
Let's hear now someone
who would not enforce the contract.
What do you say to Patrick?
Why not?
Yes.
Well, I mean,
I agree.
I think the contract should be upheld
when all the parties know all the information.
But in this case,
I don't think there's a way a mother
before the child exists
could actually know
how she's going to feel about that child.
So I don't think the mother
actually had all the information.
She didn't know the person
that was going to be born
and didn't know how much she would love that person.
So that's my argument.
So you would not,
and what's your name?
Evan Wilson.
Evan says he would not uphold the contract
because when it was entered into,
the surrogate mother couldn't
be expected to know in advance
how she would feel.
So she didn't really have
the relevant information
when she made that contract.
Who else?
Who else would not uphold the contract?
Yes?
I think,
I also think that a contract
should generally be uphold,
but I think that the child
has an inalienable right
to its actual mother.
And I think that if that mother wants it,
then that child should have
the right to that mother.
You mean the biological mother,
not the adoptive mother?
Right.
And why is that?
First of all, tell me your name.
Anna.
Anna. Why is that Anna?
Because I think that
that bond that is created
by nature is stronger than any bond
that is created by, you know, a contract.
Good. Thank you.
Who else?
Yes?
I disagree.
I don't think that a child has
an inalienable right
to her biological mother.
I think that adoption and surrogacy
are both legitimate trade-offs.
And I agree with the point made
that it's a voluntary agreement.
An individual made it.
It's a voluntary agreement.
And you can't,
okay,
apply coercion to this argument.
You can't apply the objection
from coercion to this argument.
Correct.
What's your name?
Kathleen.
Kathleen, what do you say to Evan
that though there may not have been,
Evan claimed that the consent was tainted,
not by coercion,
but by lack of adequate information.
She couldn't have known
the relevant information,
namely how she would feel about the child.
What do you say to that?
I don't think the emotional content
of her feelings plays into this.
I think in a case of law,
in the justice of this scenario,
her change of feelings are not relevant.
If I give up my child for adoption
and then I decide later on
that I really want that child back,
too bad.
It's a trade-off.
It's a trade-off that the mother has made.
So a deal is a deal.
You agree with Patrick.
I agree with Patrick.
A deal is a deal.
Yes.
Good.
I would say that though I'm not really sure
if I agree with the idea
that the child has a right to their mother,
I think the mother definitely
has a right to her child.
And I also think that there are some areas
where market forces shouldn't necessarily penetrate.
I think that the whole surrogate mother area
smacks a little bit of dealing in human beings.
It seems dehumanizing.
And it doesn't really seem right.
So that's my main reason.
And what is, could, tell us your name.
I'm Andrew.
Andrew.
What is dehumanizing about buying and selling
the right to a child for money?
What is dehumanizing about it?
Well, because you're buying someone's biological right.
I mean, you can't,
in the law as it said,
you can't sell your own child.
Like were you to have a child,
I believe that the law prohibits you
selling it to another person or selling it…
So this is like baby selling.
Right.
To a certain extent.
I mean, though there is a contract
with another person, you've made agreements and whatnot,
there is an undeniable emotional bond that
takes place between a mother and a child.
And it's wrong to simply ignore
this because you've written out something contractually.
All right.
You want to reply to Andrew?
Stay there.
You point out there's an undeniable emotional bond.
I feel like in this situation, we're not
necessarily arguing against adoption or surrogacy in itself.
We're just sort of pointing out the emotional differences.
But wait.
I mean, it's easy to break everything down
to numbers and say, oh, we have contracts
like you're buying and selling a car.
But there are underlying emotions.
I mean, you're dealing with people.
I mean, these are not
objects to be bought and sold.
All right.
What about Andrew's claim that this is like baby selling?
I believe that adoption and surrogacy should be permitted.
Whether or not I actually will
partake in it is not really relevant.
But I think that the government
should give its citizens the rights to...
To allow for adoption and surrogacy.
But adoption.
Adoption is not...
According to the law...
Is adoption baby selling?
Well, do you think you should be able
to bid for a baby that's up for adoption?
That's Andrew's challenge.
Do I think I should be
able to bid for a baby?
I'm not sure.
It's a market.
I mean, I feel like the
extent to which it's been applied...
I'm not sure if...
I'm not sure if the government
should be able to permit it.
And I have to think about it more, but...
All right.
Fair enough.
Are you satisfied, Andrew?
Well, yeah.
I mean, I just...
I think surrogacy should be permitted.
I think that people can do it.
But I don't think that it should be
forced upon people that once the contract is signed,
it's absolutely like the end all.
I think that it's unenforceable.
So people should be free, Andrew, to enter
into these contracts, but it should not be
enforceable in a court?
In a court, no.
Who would like to join
on one side or the other?
Yes.
I think I have an interesting perspective
on this because my brother was actually one
of the people who donated to a sperm bank
and he was paid a very large amount of money.
He was six feet tall, but not blonde.
He had dimples, though.
So he actually has...
He what?
I'm an aunt now and he has a daughter.
He donated his sperm to a lesbian couple in Oklahoma.
And he has...
He has been contacted by them and he
has seen pictures of his daughter, but he still
does not feel an emotional bond to his daughter.
He just has a sense of curiosity about what
she looks like and what she's doing and how
she is.
He doesn't feel love for his child.
So from this experience, I think the bond
between a mother and a child cannot be compared
to the bond between the father and the child.
That's really interesting.
What's your name?
Vivian.
So we've got the case of surrogacy, commercial surrogacy.
And it's been compared to baby selling
and we've been exploring whether that analogy
is apt.
And it can also be compared,
as you point out, to sperm selling.
But you're saying that sperm selling and
baby selling or even surrogacy are very different.
Yes.
They're unequal services.
And that's because, Vivian, you
say that the tie, the bond...
Yes.
And also the time investment that's given
by a mother, nine months, cannot be compared
to a man going into a sperm
bank, looking at pornography, depositing into a cup.
I don't think those are equal.
Good.
All right.
So we...
Because that's what I'm saying.
I'm sorry.
That's what happens in a sperm bank.
All right.
So this is really interesting.
We have...
All right.
Notice the arguments that have come out so far.
The objections to surrogacy, the objections to
enforcing that contract are of at least
two kinds.
There was the objection about tainted consent.
This time, not because of...
Coercion or implicit coercion, but
because of imperfect or flawed information.
So tainted or flawed consent can arise either
because of coercion or because of a lack of
relevant information, at least according
to one argument that we've heard.
And then a second objection
to enforcing the surrogacy contract.
Okay.
So the argument is, it's not through the law.
This is through the law, by the way.
Okay.
The argument is, it's not through
the law, but by the way.
And what is it, by the way?
I think it's a very long argument.
Well, let's look at the argument on the other side.
Okay.
So the argument on the other side.
What happened in the second part, the argument
on the other side of the equation, it's a
little bit of a puzzle.
It's a little bit of a puzzle.
When this case was decided by the
courts, what did they say about these arguments?
The law court ruled that the contract was enforceable.
Neither party had a superior bargaining position.
A price for the service was
struck and a bargain was reached.
One side didn't force the other.
Neither had disproportionate bargaining power.
Then it went to the New Jersey Supreme Court.
And what did they do? They said this contract
is not enforceable. They did grant custody to
Mr. Stern as the father because they thought
that would be in the best interest of
the child, but they restored the rights of Mary
Beth Whitehead and left it to lower
courts to decide exactly what the visitation rights
should be. They invoked two different kinds
of reasons along the lines that Andrew proposed.
First, there was not sufficiently informed
consent, the court argued. Under the contract,
the natural mother is irrevocably committed before
she knows the strength of her bond
with her child. She never makes a truly voluntary informed
decision.
For any decision prior to the baby's
birth is, in the most important sense, uninformed.
That was the court. Then, the court also
made a version of the second argument against commodification
in this kind of case. This is the sale of
a child, the court said, or at the very least,
the sale of a mother's right to
her child. Whatever idealism may motivate the participation
of knowledges, there does not matter
what you draw from anonymous information. Barайте
can somehow enter a parallel with his family because
he has access to the right to an asset
they have been carrying for you.
procreation and to reproduction.
How persuasive are they?
There was, it's true, a
voluntary agreement, a contract struck,
between William Stern and Mary Beth Whitehead.
But there are at least two ways
that consent can be other than truly free.
First, if people are pressured
or coerced to give their agreement,
and second, if their consent is not truly informed.
And in the case of surrogacy, the court said,
a mother can't know, even one
who already has kids of her own,
what it would be like to bear
a child and give it up for pay.
So in order to assess criticism, objection number one,
we have to figure out just how
free does a voluntary exchange have to be
with respect to the bargaining power and equal information.
Question number one.
How do we assess the second objection?
The second objection is more elusive, it's more difficult.
Andrew acknowledged this, right?
What does it mean to say there is something dehumanizing
to make childbearing a market transaction?
Well, one of the philosophers we read on this subject,
Elizabeth Anderson, tries to give some,
bring some philosophical clarity to
the unease that Andrew articulated.
She said, by requiring the surrogate mother to require
to repress whatever parental love she feels for the child,
surrogacy contracts convert women's labor
into a form of alienated labor.
The surrogate's labor is alienated because
she must divert it from the end,
from the end which the
social practices of pregnancy rightly promote,
namely an emotional bond with her child.
So what Anderson is suggesting is,
that certain goods should not be treated
as open to use or to profit.
Certain goods are properly valued in ways other than use.
What are other ways of valuing and treating
goods that should not be open to use?
Anderson says there are many.
Respect.
Appreciation.
Love.
Honor.
Awe.
Sanctity.
There are many modes of valuation beyond use,
and certain goods are not properly valued
if they're treated simply as objects of use.
How do we go about evaluating that argument of Anderson?
In a way it takes us back
to the debate we had with utilitarianism.
Is use the only way to use?
Is utility, is use the
only proper way of treating goods,
including life, military service, procreation, childbearing?
And if not, how do we figure out,
how can we determine what modes of
valuation are fitting or appropriate to those goods?
Several years ago there was a scandal surrounding a doctor,
an infertility specialist in Virginia named Cecil Jacobson.
He didn't have a donor
catalog because unknown to his patients,
all of the sperm he used to
inseminate his patients came from one donor,
Dr. Jacobson himself.
At least one woman who testified in court
was unnerved at how much her newborn daughter
looked just like him.
Now it's possible to condemn Dr. Jacobson
for failing to inform the women in advance.
That would be the argument about consent.
The columnist Ellen Goodman described
the bizarre scenario as follows.
Dr. Jacobson, she wrote, gave
his infertility business the personal touch.
But now the rest of us, she wrote,
are in for a round
of second thoughts about sperm donation.
Goodman concluded that fatherhood
should be something you do,
not something you donate.
And I think what she was doing,
and what the philosopher Elizabeth Anderson is doing,
and what Andrew was suggesting
with his argument about dehumanization,
is pondering whether there are certain goods,
that money shouldn't buy,
not just because of tainted consent,
but also perhaps because certain goods are properly
valued in a way higher than mere use.
Those at least are the
questions we are going to pursue
with the help of some
philosophers in the weeks to come.
Join the conversation.
Take a pop quiz.
Watch lectures you've missed and learn a lot more.
Visit justiceharvard.org.
It's the right thing to do.